Even if I see your diff is gonna blow up
production, I will comment on it and be
like, "This is gonna blow up production
and then accept it and be like, "Yeah,
make sure you fix that first." Right.
This is Jake Bullum. He's a principal
engineer or IC8 at Instagram who got
promoted twice from staff engineer. So,
I think IC8 was like, "So, let's go and
put him on one of the projects we have
that is like impossible and everyone
thinks it's stupid." And yet, his work
life balance is somehow reasonable. So,
you have pretty good balance. Yes. And
it's all the systems that I've been
building my whole career that I think
are like able to keep me here. Yeah, you
probably want to know about. I thought
he had a really interesting note-taking
system. And my note-taking system is
actually in VS Code. And he shared a lot
more than you might think. I'm also a
bit of a loose unit and sometimes say
dumb stuff. Here's the full
episode. Your work has such insane blast
radius cuz you got to I8 or principal
engineer in the industry. on your path
to IC8. What were you hired in as to
Meta and maybe you can give a high level
timeline of the teams you were on? Yeah,
sure thing. Yeah, so I came into Meta as
a six and actually joined Facebook
groups at the time. So groups went from
I don't know 10 or 15 people to like 700
in like 2 or 3 years. Wow. But yeah, so
I joined right at the peak of it like
700. Yeah. And I was on some team like
groups integrity was actually pretty
wild for They had a pretty slow ramp up
to meta because I joined when they we it
was middle of co co had just started so
they hadn't really figured out remote
onboarding yet so it was really slow and
then I joined my team and the election
was coming so no one could really ramp
me up so I was just kind of operating
solo on like random stuff so yeah I had
a really slow start to meta for most
people so actually empathize with a lot
of people that like took like a year to
ramp up instead of like 3 months was
your performance at risk initially
because you were onboarding remotely or
I think my manager like help helped a
lot like with the system and I managed
to get like a meets all or something
like this you know definitely wasn't
excelling and had a few little projects
that like probably helped them sell that
but yeah I'm pretty sure they told this
like slow onboarding story during PSC
which was kind of crazy uh especially
cuz groups was like so critical at the
time right they had so many engineers
and right after that actually just I
just decided to switch teams because I
had some friends on Instagram and they
were like, "Yo, come and work
on Instagram web and this is this has
actually been a bit of a theme
throughout my career. So I joined Meta
to work on UIs, right? To work on web to
use React. I loved React and I joined
this group's integrity team. We weren't
doing really any of that." Like I was
doing it like 20% of the time, but most
of the time it was backend systems,
right? So I was like, "Okay, cool. I'll
move to this team." So is your
background before Meta all more like
full stack or front end work? Yeah, so I
spent I started coding at a really young
age and it was always on the front end
and then when I went to companies I
would like to do like front-end product
and every single company I've ever
worked at moved me into like front-end
infrastructure very quickly and then
backend infrastructure. And actually one
of my big draws to Meta was, oh, they're
so big. I'll always be able to work on
front-end product, right? Like
specializing. Yeah. And this thing
continued where I got pulled into
Instagram now to do front-end product
and was like awesome. Within a couple
months I was on the front end
infrastructure team. Yeah. Yeah. In
Instagram. And then yeah within like a
year I was on the backend infrastructure
teams and I was like oh it doesn't
matter which company I'm at. How do you
how do you keep getting pulled to the
back end? Like what is drawing you? I
think well now because you've done it so
many times you end up knowing like a lot
about it and like all the different like
architecture and systems that you have
to sort of put together and it it just
it is more impactful now right with the
big switch to mobile uh the only thing
that's like rivaling it is the server
right like web has become such a small
amount of our traffic you've got to go
to where the more important stack is I
see so generally you are picking
projects based off of where the impact
is and that is leading you to go to
backend stuff or like Yeah, exactly.
Like on at Instagram at web we probably
had like less than 100 people would work
on it, you know, around the company part
time and on the back end we have like
2,000 3,000 engineers working on it.
Yeah, that makes sense. So even from the
engineering point of view. Yeah. Right.
Right. So then so then you were IC6 on
the group's team. You were on boarding
slowly and you weren't liking it. It was
this backend integrity system. You
switched to Instagram web as a IC6. Is
that Yes. Okay. And so it that's where
your career started to really pick up.
Yes. So I think I came in and like had
all the skill sets. So I was like
basically ramped up immediately and like
landing impact immediately. And my
managers on the team at the time
recognized that I was like pretty
strong. And we were we were growing too.
They were moving from one of our stacks
to another stack, right? and they were
like, "Hey, we're going to have like two
or three teams. What do you think about
like stretching to be the Uber TL across
these teams, right? Cuz that's six to
seven carriers started. You're not on
one team anymore. You're kind of leading
like a bunch of teams, right?" And I was
like, "Yeah, I think I can do it." So,
they kind of gave me the opportunity to
like do that, right? Why do you think
they came to you for the opportunity?
Because, yeah, I think that's one of the
big things people look for, you know?
I people who want to get to these levels
they even if they want to sometimes they
don't have the opportunity. So yeah I'm
curious what did you do that that you
think made them come to you and say hey
we want you to do the IC7 thing. So when
I was actually joining the team it was
something that I was like looking
forward to. So I was like yeah I want
the career growth right. I think I can
do this. Like I my previous companies I
was actually leading four teams before I
came to Meta. So Meta likes to down
level you, right? So I went from leading
four teams to one team when I came to
Meta. Yeah. So they were like, "Yeah,
like we'll see what happens in the first
month and if you're like crushing it,
we'll like give you that opportunity."
So I came in and in the first month like
did what they needed. So they like,
"Okay, here we go." So when you like
even before you switched, you said,
"Hey, FYI, I'm I'm eager for IC7." And
Yeah. And so they knew that and they
basically just gave you the opportunity
because and to see if you could do it.
Yeah. So they knew that about me and
then they knew that they needed it on
the team too. Right. Right. Right.
Right. So you talked about what is IC7
scope? What does IC7 scope look like?
Yeah. Uh so IC7 scope to me looks like
Yeah. So six is like you're basically
like the TL of a team, right? Maybe 10
12 people. It really depends on your
team though. If you're on like a really
complicated part of the stack or
something, maybe your team skews
differently, but generally like that. Or
if you're on a really easy part, maybe
it skews the other way. But generally
like yeah, six is leading one team and
then seven is like across multiple teams
or across like a a different area,
right? So then would eight be even just
like another step of that progression?
Yeah. So eight just keeps going up too,
right, for different teams like your
blast radius. And yeah, this is all
dependent on how important the problem
is that you're working on, right?
Working on the backend infrastructure,
right? If you're impacting 3,000
engineers by like making your frameworks
better, right? And it's taking a lot to
make those frameworks better, right?
Right. You need like hundreds of people
to make those frameworks better. Yeah.
Like you're hitting pretty big blast
radius. Yeah. So then your archetype is
leading through other because there's
also the other ones like framework
specialist kind of someone that just
digs deep somewhere and speeds up a
thousand people but is not directing a
thousand people. Maybe you can talk
about like the archetypes you Yeah.
Yeah. So this I'm Yeah. Talking through
one very specific lens, right? So yeah,
there's all these ways that people can,
you know, contribute to the business and
like be having that large blast impact.
And yeah, the most extreme other end of
the spectrum is like the specialties,
right? So you've got the guys that are
like, I don't know, deep on the compiler
or like Yeah, they change like 10 lines
of code down there and it saves the
business, you know, hundreds of millions
of dollars. So like a fixer, like the
fixers. Yeah. So you've got you've got
this range, right, that you can do it
in. And maybe they don't like talking to
people, right? They don't like running
around. Yeah. But we still realize
there's like really good value in having
these folks around and give them the
career path, too. Yeah. Yeah,
definitely. Were you intentional about
the archetype that you picked for
yourself as you grew to ICA? So, I guess
not really. My philosophy is always just
do whatever it takes to get whatever
project I'm on done. M but you know I'm
leaning into my strengths and my
strengths are like talking to people
like being able to yeah coordinate
people. I like to think I'm like fun and
happy to be around which gives people
like you know some motivation other than
work to be there and like you know most
of the projects I'm on are like marathon
projects so we get to stick around for
like a long time together and have some
fun right so you're like a force
multiplier like you take a group of
people and you make them some percentage
better because of you know your
behaviors. Yeah, maybe that maybe that's
what happens but I don't think about it
like that. M I'm just trying to get us
all doing the same thing. And I see the
good in people, right? And I like see
the strengths in people. I just want
people around me to succeed. So I'm just
trying to make them succeed. And I guess
that ends up, you know, compounding and
being best for all of us. Like have you
ever thought about management? Cuz like
a lot of what you just described, I feel
like there's some overlap there. I've
done some brief stints in management
before meta. Yeah. And yeah, I think
it's just it's not for me because I like
to be able to then like if the project
needs it, go and like, you know, land
500 diffs in a couple of months or
whatever. Like go and land a ton of code
to get us across the line. I see. You
can't really do that in management.
Yeah. I'm also a bit of a loose unit and
sometimes say dumb stuff. So I think I
need it's better if I'm not in
management and like have people in
management who can check me on that, you
know, occasionally when it's needed.
Right. Right. Right. Right. That makes
sense. Yeah. I feel like you have to be
a little more sensitive to things as a
as a manager. Yes. Yeah. I noticed your
internal profile said something like
always open for a chat or something like
that. But my view of an ICA is someone
who's drowning in responsibilities and
does not have time. Yeah. Why do you
make time for or you know make yourself
available like that if your time is like
so precious? So yeah, definitely you
know you're getting worked a lot at IC8
and you're you are overloaded but yeah
I'll always make time for someone who
will who is reaching out about something
right you know maybe maybe I'll be
completely overload and the meeting has
to be like a few weeks from now but
there's a lot of value in being
accessible to everyone right like anyone
can come to you and be like hey I have
this idea or I have this problem like
can you help me and you're just like
helping your org or you learn about a
problem that you wouldn't have known
about otherwise, right? I kind of wonder
though cuz someone like you is probably
getting so many, you know, outreaches.
Like I would have thought you'd have to
pick and choose a bit, you know, like
let's say intern comes to you and is
just excited and wants a coffee chat or
something. In a in a in a nice perfect
world, you'd make time for them and you
talk to them. But yep, in a impact
driven world, some things are going to
need to be dropped. What are your
thoughts on picking and choosing your
time? Yeah. So, I I do try to put the
levels thing out of my head always. So,
if an intern come, I try to treat them
the same as everyone else. So, if they
came and they were like asking good
questions, right, or like, you know,
you're giving you're telling them stuff
and they're like acting on it and going
for it, you know, I'm probably likely to
give them more time again. But if they
come in and they like kind of ignore it
or they ask really bad questions and
stuff, probably not likely to give them
too much time again, right? This is
assuming I had time in the first place.
Yeah. If I'm completely overloaded, like
it'll be like, "Hey, sorry, like can we
do it in a month or this is here's
another person that you can chat to,
right? Who would be better and helpful,
right?" Yeah. You mentioned So just
trying my best, I guess. Right. Right.
To a certain point. You mentioned bad
questions and good questions and I think
a lot of people who are earlier in their
career that's something that they're
thinking about a lot is should they ask
or not what's good what's bad. Yeah. Do
you have any tips on how to make your
questions
good? Haven't really thought about it
too much but I don't I don't know. Just
be
be be genuine, right? Don't try and like
script it or like pick up line it
like Yeah. Just be genuine about what
you want to ask or find out. Yeah. Yeah.
Because then naturally you'll find the
right person, right? If you ask me one
of these questions that is like very
helpful for you and I know someone
better who can answer it, who has more
time, right, then you're going to end up
with someone better who has more time
and it's going to be better for you in
the long run. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Before
we leave the IC7 IC8, Yeah. I'm curious,
you mentioned there was a big migration
that got you promoted to IC7 and you
were leading few teams and your
management chain said we need we need a
leader and you were eager and you you
took that on. What was it for IC8?
Yeah. Also just just on that like
getting to the seven one you got to also
land the project, right?
So yeah, definitely. I think something
that happened that helped with the 71 is
I was like sort of seen as this person
that would like come in and like fix it
or get it back on track, right? So we
were doing this this back the the infra
migration and it was scoped at like 2
years or something. Yeah. And we came in
and it wasn't just me like I came in and
like we all started chatting and stuff
and we got excited and we actually ended
up delivering like the majority of it in
like 6 months which was like crazy. No
one expected that. which meant that we
can then move 90% of the resources Yeah.
onto other stuff which actually let us
put ads on Instagram web the following
half. Yeah. Which was also like a year
behind and then we shipped it got on the
team and shipped it in like 3 months
which was kind of crazy. That's kind of
crazy. So how how did you take something
that was two years and make it happen?
Did you cut scope or did you Yeah. What
happened? Yeah, we cut scope, but I
think more it was just like everyone on
the team got got hungry for it and was
like, "Yo, two years is silly. Like we
can do this sooner." Like we' started to
gel together, right? Everybody was sort
of playing to their strengths, which you
like hear is pretty common. And we're
like, "Yeah, we can do this like way
sooner than 2 years." Yeah. Yeah. I
think before we were going very
seriously too, like we were doing like
one page at a time. Yeah. And someone
was like, "Yo, why don't we do like a
100 pages?" And we're like, "Okay, let's
try it." So then we tried it and it was
like, you know, really hard at first
because we've just done 100 pages, but
then we had all the like compounding
effects of putting it all together. So
that was like accelerating us. So we
were like switching parts of the
strategy, too. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
How how did you get that team so excited
about it? I can't take all the credit
because I don't know what happens. These
situations are organic. You just start
talking about it and then people like
bouncing off each other and doing it.
But yeah, I was just bringing some some
of that hungry energy and I guess it was
infectious and then everybody was like
on board with it. We're all having fun
and we're like, "Yeah, we want to do
great." And like cuz we shipped it
early, right? It was it was good for me,
but it was good for everyone else, too,
right? Yeah. Lots of promotions on the
team. Yeah. Yeah. And it super
deserving. I mean, that's insane
business impact. Like such a huge thing.
Exactly. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah, cuz then we
got ads on there and then I I can't
remember but we're pulling in like a
bunch of money on a surface that had
never been monetized. Right. Right.
Right. Which wasn't slated to happen for
a long time. So yeah. Yeah. Yeah. That
makes sense. So and that was the IC7
promo. So that was the IC7 promo. So I
think IC8 was like at this point
leadership like identifies you and like
knows okay so Jake is the type of person
we can go and throw on problems that no
one else really wants to work on or is
like really hard to move or the rest of
the org thinks is stupid and impossible
so let's go and put him on one of the
projects we have that is like impossible
impossible and everyone thinks it's
stupid. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Which was like
we're just on the front end moving it
into the into the main meta stack.
Right. Hey, can you like move the back
end into the main meta stack? And I was
like, cool, that sounds impossible.
Let's let's try that. And that's yeah,
you you're aware of the details of the
project. But that that was an
interesting one because yeah, 95% of the
engineering org was like, "This is
stupid. Why would we waste any
resources?" Yeah. On this, right? So, we
knew we wanted to migrate into the other
stack, but we couldn't go out to the
engineering or and say, "Hey, we're
migrating." because we'd get shot down
and like everyone would be like this is
the dumbest thing ever and we'd like
kill morale for the orgs. So we're like
okay what can we do? All right,
everyone's having this problem with
interacting between these two stacks
that we have. All right, we're going to
go and fix the devx between the two
stacks. And we made a big deal about
fixing the devx between the two stacks.
Yeah. Yeah. For the first year. I see.
Yeah. So I mean you said people would
think it's stupid. You're talking about
the people who are using the existing IG
backend stack and are used to it and
they're saying what it works why switch
over. Yes. Those Okay. Yeah. And so you
had to you couldn't just immediately
initiate a migration of infrastructure
that thousands of engineers are using
without bringing them along and saying
look it's a good experience still. Yes.
Yeah. I think so. So, and also I kind of
like at the time I like agree with those
engineers, right? Like the majority of
our development is in this stack. All
our important surfaces are here. Like
it's way better to be in one. And I'm
like, "Yeah, this is true." But like our
other stack was growing in usage. There
was already all this cross stuff
happening. So like I don't know 30 or
40% of the org were impacted by this,
right? but it maybe wasn't hitting the
point where it was worth justifying
putting like a hundred people on it to
like move it move it all across, right?
So, we did the building blocks, right?
Like, okay, let's make the highway
between the two better, which is like no
one's really going to argue against that
cuz they're like they come across it
occasionally and they're like, oh, that
would make my life better, so we'll do
that. And then on the other side, okay,
there's stuff missing from dubdubdub. So
that was the first year and the second
year it's like there's a bunch of stuff
missing from dubdubdub that doesn't make
it feel like Instagram. Mhm. Let's go
and add all that stuff in there so it's
actually easier to build in there. So
that was year two. We went and did that.
Mhm. Uh now we're in year three where
it's like okay now we have these two
things and during that time more of the
crossstack stuff has happened right some
surfaces did migrate because they were
going to get bigger benefits. Uh now
we've kind of got to the point where
people are like, "Okay, we see the
writing on the wall, like how can we get
in there as fast as possible, right?"
And now we're in like full migration
mode. And so the IC8 promo cuz I guess
the full migration is not fully
complete, but there was some milestone
in this larger strategy that was worth
an IC8 promo. Yeah, I think so. So I
think this project like at some point
someone came to me and was like, "Yo,
should be running this project." or
something who's like a very senior
engineer at Meta like I don't know 10 or
10 or 11. He's been around a while cuz
the project was like it was it was so
crazy trying to re rewrite Instagram
right while you know the classic
metaphor of like you know you're on the
plane you got to switch the whole plane
while you're still on it. Yeah. So yeah
this project was scoped at like you know
many IC8s worth of scope or an IC9 or
something. Yeah. And we only had uh
sevens working on it at the time. So
there was space for that if you were
like going to do it. And then we had we
hit a couple of big milestones, right?
So we had some of these surface
milestones we had hit as well as we'd
hit pretty big traffic ones. So we'd hit
like massive milestones, right? Right.
But yeah, that was still enough to be
like, okay, yeah, they've done a lot of
work. Yeah, there's 150 teams involved.
There's like it's moving everything that
is being moved is like, you know, 20%
faster or is like way easier to work on.
Okay. Okay. Okay. I mean, yeah, that
blast radius is insane. I mean, it makes
a lot of sense. Yeah. One thing I was
curious about because you this is one of
those projects where you're switching
out a lot of the infrastructure that
people are using. How did you make sure
all these engineers are happy with the
tooling? Cuz you're you're switching it
out while they're doing their day-to-day
work. Did you I don't know have some
sort of way to engage the community and
keep them happy?
Uh yeah. So we have like at Instagram we
have like a a group of people we call
our server champions. Oh right. Right.
And I think you have these like sort of
horizontal groups in many orgs. I've had
them at previous companies too. Right.
They're always called different things.
I don't know the server guild or
whatever. You just need when you have so
many teams people from all around the
org to kind represent the platform that
you're working on. And you want like
some people from your infra teams, but
you want majority people from your
product teams because infra teams can
get quite disconnected from how
day-to-day developments happen. Yeah. So
we had those folks. So we would always
like it's basically a continuous channel
like we have a chat group and stuff,
right? I think there's about 40 of us.
Yeah. So they're always giving us
feedback. We're always asking for
feedback. If stuff's coming up, we're
asking them to like let us know, right?
Like if someone on the team raises it to
them, let us know. Mhm. I think that's
actually like probably our most
important feedback channel. We do have
the big feedback channels of like, you
know, the 2,000 person groups where
people can post in Devx feedback like
but we find it has to be really bad by
the time it gets posted in that group
and we probably know about it already.
Whereas these server champion groups
like we might know about it within an
hour or two, right, of something rolling
out or breaking. Yeah. In addition to
like all the metrics that we monitor,
which are very helpful, too. Yeah. Yeah,
that makes sense. As you've grown from
IC6 to IC8, you take on more
responsibility. How's your your like
hours worked per week changed over the
over time? Yeah. So, I think sometimes I
get really excited at work and I'll be
like working like, you know, 60 hour
weeks or something like that, 70 hour
weeks. Mh. Uh and then other times like,
okay, let's get this back under control.
And I'll like drop it down to like, you
know, my 40hour weeks. So if it's during
the summer and I worked 60our weeks
during the winter, I'll be like, "Okay,
I'm going to do 35 hour weeks during the
summer or something." Yeah. Yeah. So it
does it does fluctuate and depends on
what the project's going on. But most of
the time I am trying to target like the
40 hours a week cuz I I want that work
life balance. I've got more to life than
just working, right? Yeah. Yeah. But
yeah, if I get really excited, I might
get into it. If I decide I need to do
more personal, I'll like bow out of it.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So you have pretty
good balance then. actually you're able
to maintain your impact with a
reasonable amount. You're not going
crazy. Yeah. Over the last 6 months.
Yes. And it's all the systems that have
been building the whole my whole career
that I think are like able to to keep me
here. Yeah. Yeah. You probably want to
know about it. Oh yeah. I got to know
about these systems then. What are these
systems that are making you able to have
this level of impact with that time
investment? So yeah, the the thing is so
definitely do shield my time. So while I
am open to people coming in, I do shield
my time. So I think like focus blocks or
Yeah, like nearly 50% of my week is
focus blocks. So I try not to do any
meetings on any mornings. So I'm a
morning person and get a lot done in the
mornings. So I will not take meetings
until after lunch. Yeah. Yeah. And
that's worked pretty well for me. In
addition to that, I try to make it so
Wednesday, Wednesdays and Fridays, I
don't have any meetings. Yeah. And then
also I'll try to put all my one-on ones
on Monday afternoons. Is there some
specific reason for beginning of the
week or just uh Nope. Nothing for
beginning of the week. I just picked a
day that I was like, "Okay, I'm going to
just do these all in a block." Yeah. And
then that leaves basically Tuesday and
Thursday afternoons for project
meetings. Yeah. Yeah. This doesn't
always work right because Yeah. I was
about to say there's every week there's
exceptions to the rule, but generally I
find that shields a lot of my time so
that I'm able to be able to do stuff to
like move the projects forward that I
need or like message people when I need
to. Right. Okay. So, focus time. What
about because you said sometimes you
just you just really focus and you do
500 diffs and like in a couple months
when you're in that hyper productive
coding state, how do you do that? Oh,
okay. Yeah. So in times where I'm doing
that, yeah, like I'll just disappear for
like two two or three week. Well, not
disappear, but like I will cancel like
lots of these meetings, right? If you
once a project's going and has momentum
or something, you can like, you know,
skip a few weeks of project updates or
sync groups if we're all together and
know exactly what we need to be doing.
Yeah. Yeah. So yeah, we'll cut out
meetings. And I think I've been praised
a little bit for like how few meetings I
have on the teams and projects that I
run. Like people are very surprised when
they come in and learn that like this
massive project doesn't have central
meetings. Yeah. Yeah. Like there there
are no meetings. Like people like, "Hey,
I want to get involved. Can you add me
to the syncs?" I'm like, "There are no
sinks." Well, how do you keep how do you
keep because those meetings have some
value. So they have some value. So this
the work streams that need to have them
will, but like overall and overarching
there isn't any. So there's not this
tiered thing. It's like if you're on a
particular work stream, right? There is
one sync for that. Yeah. Yeah. You don't
have to go to like a series of syncs
where it's like, okay, we need to go to
this one and then I need to go to like
this level one and this level one. Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. Is there some high leverage
like leads kind of meeting? So there
isn't. So there isn't that. Yeah. But
there is probably a core group of like
you know 15 TLS across the different
areas, but we don't all just sit in a
meeting and meet together. If we need to
we'll like chat in a chat in a group,
but we don't even have a chat group.
There's not even a chat. There's not
even a chat group. as it's all ad hoc as
needed. It's all as h ad hoc as needed.
And like if we need to have some of
these conversations, we'll just push it
into the wider forums. Yeah. Or if there
does need to be a thing that's like
sensitive or something and we do need to
chat about it together, we we will do
the ad hoc stuff. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah. I like that. I mean, most
recurring cadences are suboptimal
because they're just static, you know?
So, yeah, I do kind of like that. Yeah.
Yeah. So, this is part of the
philosophy, too. always be available,
right? So, if someone needs to talk to
me that day, I will find time to like
talk to that person, right? Yeah.
Whether it's like I have to be out, I'm
out going for lunch or something, I'll
take the phone call. Like, I'll do
meetings in all sorts of weird places to
make sure that people like have the info
they need and they're on the floor.
Right. Right. Right. And in those times
where you're a coding machine, are you
also diff machine and what's it look
like? Yeah, whatever's needed. I
actually usually when I fire up and I'm
getting in the zone, I'll quickly I'll
go to the diffs first because anyone
who's got a needs review diff, right?
Like they're se semilocked or like
they're not being able to land what
they're landing. So yeah, I'll go
through all of that first, get that in
before I even start coding myself and
every hour I'll go back and check again.
Yeah. Yeah. Oh wow. So you're like
really on top of diff review then.
Really on top of diff reviews. Yeah.
Like actually I think there's probably
lots of memes floating around for me cuz
like people put up diffs and like 5
minutes later it's like stamp on me and
they're like what the hell is going on?
And that's a lot because I'm on top of
it, but also because I have this
philosophy on like diff reviews and risk
where yeah, if like if I don't think the
diff is risky, right, you're getting a
very rudimentary review and like
basically you can put that code in like
so if it's like gated, it's not on a
core system, right? These things then
you're going to just get a very high
level diff and then basically I'm just
like trusting you. So um you're saying
you you modulate your level of time
investment based on how risky the diff
is ba based on how risky the diff is
right. So if you're rewriting it, right,
we're it it's all gated right now and we
just want the highle trunk architecture
to be correct. If you're working on like
some child component or something, it's
like cool, it's gated. It's not critical
to the system. Like yeah, I'm trusting
you to do whatever you need to do over
there. So you'll just stamp it stamp
stamp it let it. Yeah. Some people view
quality different view as a uh like an
important thing rather than just
stamping. So you ever get push back on?
This is my controversial one for sure.
So yeah, so I I think that is correct
for like the the trunk of the system,
the core core parts of the system or
anything that's already live in prod
like is going to get pretty thorough
review. Yeah. If it's not live and prod
and it is one of these sub like subp
parts of the system or less critical
things like I'll still skim it to make
sure you didn't do anything like
absolutely crazy like introduce like I
don't know security issues or you know
start mining crypto on our servers or
something but uh yeah I'll just like let
let that let that fly in. Yeah, I I mean
it makes sense. So you're basically
trading off speed for I guess quality,
but it's not dumb quality. It's like
these are places where it makes sense to
make the trade-off where you make Yeah.
So you can have like lower quality
components for like these the child the
child parts of the system, right? Or the
leaf parts of the system. And also these
parts are like generally easier to unit
test. If they do fail, they only blow up
like a small part of it, right? Just a
little blow up. Just a little part of
it. If it is badly architected, it's
only on this like tiny part of the
system. It's not impacting, you know,
hundreds of engineers. Maybe it impacts
a couple and someone one day is like,
"What the hell's up with this?" Doesn't
take a long time to rewrite. Right.
Right. If you mess up the architecture
in the core trunk, probably takes like
hundreds of people a long time to like
fix. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Have you have you
ever had someone I remember early in my
career I was all about speed and I was
approving some diffs and then someone
would come back to me and say why'd you
approve this that was too you know like
let's slow down a little bit on this
they get some feedback or someone says
hey you know calm down like this defin
this definitely happens actually
interesting thing
so teach the people close to me in my
teams that like hey it's okay
I stamped your diff to like put it back
in review again if you actually need
deeper review or like flag it flag it in
the summary or the test plan like or
comment on it like hey I'm actually
looking for a deep review on this if you
know that's how our team operates now.
Yeah. Um and this is actually really
good because I might have thought it's
like a child part of the system and
maybe it is still a child part of the
system but they've thought hey this is
like could be like more performant or
like I actually want you to double check
this. U so then we use that signal to be
like okay this person actually wants
things. So if I missed it even if they
put a comment on it they'll throw it
back into review and like be like need
real review or something like that cuz
they knew they knew what happened. Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. I see that makes
sense. But yeah there's definitely this
is not the philosophy of everyone at
Meta, right? Like we most people it's
like quality high quality for
everything. Yeah. And it depends on the
system though. It depends on the system.
Also depends on like this is like trust
you build on your team too. on the team
probably not going to get this treatment
for the first couple of weeks. Although
I do want to defer to like how do I
accept this diff, not how do I reject
this diff, which I think is an important
philosophy to have. Why is that? Yeah.
Uh cuz like I'm not trying to like knit
your code and get you to write it the
exact way I would write it, right? I'm
trying to be like, okay, what is
absolutely blocking this thing from
going to going to production? like big
highle architecture things like I don't
know some critical bugs like is it going
to blow up prod right not like write it
exactly the way I would write it right I
think that takes a while to get to too
right like more senior engineers usually
become amendable to this but when you're
in yeah when you're like in the first
five years of your career maybe you've
only seen a few ways of writing it right
so you want people to write it that
exact way yeah yeah definitely I I think
when you're working in a team where
there's high trust And you get to the
point where people they have feedback
but they accept with nits, you know. I I
love that because you just everyone just
trusting each other, you know, move
fast. Yeah. And I have some feedback,
but it's not that important. It's just
like take it if you will. Man, this is
where I push that needle even further
again. So, I will like even if I see
your diff is going to blow up
production,
I will I will comment on it and be like,
"This is going to blow up production."
And then accept it and be like, "Yeah,
make sure you fix that first." Right.
And I've never had a case where
someone's like landed it with a comment
on it that says, "Hey, this is going to
blow up production." Cuz you can imagine
like sitting in review or something and
someone's like, "The diff had a comment
on it. This is going to blow up
production." And it blow up. That's wild
that. Yeah. Except I just trust them to
fix it, right? Like Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
Fix it the right way. Once again, if
they have trust, if it's like a new
person on the team and I'm not sure if
they're going to fix it the right way,
right? I might be like, "Ping me again
when it's like ready." Yeah. Yeah. But
yeah, 99% of the time I'll just like
accept and go. And yeah, haven't had to
do the thing where I pull back because
I've never had one that's been shipped
accidentally exploded.
And that's actually a little bit of a
philosophy I use across like I guess
building these systems, judging how fast
I'm moving. Yeah. If I'm doing something
and it's not I'm not getting feedback
that it's like broken or I'm not seeing
negative effects from it, right? Even if
it is controversial and crazy, I'll keep
pushing the boundary on it, right? U
same as our rollouts like if we're at 1%
we're getting like very little feedback
and like metrics are looking good and we
might move to like 10% the next day and
people like that's crazy like step to
like two three five things it's like
well not we're not getting any like
signals that it's not going poorly as
soon as we get signals that it's going
poorly we start pulling back but
otherwise I find you like move too
slowly right you want to be moving at
like the fastest speed you can without
ruining things right so if you're not
getting if you're not making anything
worse like keep trying to find that
edge. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. I I had a tech
lead early in my career and I had taken
down prod or something and I was talking
to him about it and he you know at one
on one end you shouldn't break prod
generally but he also said if you never
break
prod that's probably not also optimal
like there there should be some level of
risk otherwise you're moving too slowly
and so yeah exactly yeah try not to
break prod But if you never break it,
you're probably like very slow and Yeah.
And if you're breaking it every day,
you're probably going way too fast.
Yeah. Exactly. Exactly. Need to fix
something. Do you use um AI at all? Yes.
So, I've been I use it. I use chat GPT
like I don't know 10 times a day outside
of work and then internally we have like
own things that I use too. But I think
it's great, right? Like just like
harness the tools that are coming. They
have a bunch of caveats and they make
mistakes and stuff, but like I don't
know. I had to use if someone said,
"Don't use a calculator," I'd be like,
"What the fuck?" Use the to use the
tool. The tool's there. Figure out a way
to use it, right? Yeah. Then maybe we
won't get replaced if we become masters
of the tools. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Exactly.
Exactly. Yeah. I wanted to talk about
being a tech lead a bit because I feel
like that's one superpower that you have
to start. What would you say is the role
of a tech lead? Like what are the
important things to do and how do you
see that role? Yeah. So yeah, people
probably have a different opinion on
this all over the place, but yeah, mine
is just like, okay, you're the tech
lead. You're responsible for this
project now, right? Like do whatever it
takes to get this project done. Usually
the highest leverage thing you can be
doing is like making sure everyone else
is like contributing to the project and
moving in the right direction, right?
But sometimes you might have to switch
and do other things like writing code or
jump into fixer mode. There's been a few
times where I've had to like no one else
can debug what this thing's doing. So, I
spent two weeks chasing like the
craziest bug through the system to like
find that line of code that's messing
up. At this point, you've probably
coached tech leads because you're in a
position with leverage. Yeah. What's the
most common mistake you see people make
if they're transitioning into more of a
leadership role? I think getting like
kind of disconnected from what the what
the goal is of the project, right? So
easy to get caught up in the day-to-day
operations of like we need to be doing
this and we need to be doing Y and like
lose track of the fact that like the
direction we're heading in might have
actually shifted a little bit and it's
like your responsibility like shift the
team towards towards the goal again.
Right. Right. I know at Meta regardless
of how high level you are you're
expected to make technical
contributions. Yeah. But generally there
is a sentiment of as you become a higher
and higher tech lead you get further and
further from the code. Yeah. And more in
doc work and leadership meetings and
things. How do you strike that balance?
Yeah. So it's definitely is uh a hard
balance to strike but I'll still I'll
still write code probably nearly nearly
every week even if it's like a smaller
amount of code because then I'm using
the full tool chain. Often it's because
no one else wants to do it or it's
something that, you know, maybe I'm
going to do it 10 times faster cuz I
know know that thing and I don't want
them to waste a week on it. So I'll go
and do it, right? Yeah. So I just I'll
just like find the time and those focus
blocks and stuff help with that too.
Right. And it might if it gets to
Wednesday and I haven't written code and
nothing's come up, I might go and do
that. Yeah. This is all caveed on the
fact that I'm always trying to work on
what I think is the most important
thing, right? Mhm. Like if it was saving
that person, you know, their whole week
of doing it, it's going to take me an
hour. I'll go and do Yeah. But there
might be periods of time where we're
doing a big review or, you know, we're
going to get a headcount injection or
I don't know, we need to be doing X, Y,
or Z and then that's way higher leverage
for me to be spending my time on and I
won't code for a few weeks. Right.
Right. How do you I think this is more,
you know, junior people lack this, but
how do you develop that skill of seeing
what is impactful with your time? I
mean, where's the ROI? Where'd you learn
that? Yeah, I think it's uh I don't
know, just like practice. Practice makes
perfect. And you've seen a lot of
scenarios, so you kind of know, right,
which one after a while. Yeah. But yeah,
when I didn't have that gauge, and I
still use this a little bit now, it's
always like, what do I what do I think
myself is really important that no one
else is willing to work on? Yeah. Um and
that's usually the area I would go to.
Before I had developed like a good sense
of it because now there'll be sometimes
where I'm like oh no one's working on it
because it's stupid but like if I really
think it's really important I will like
find a way to work on it. Yeah. Oh
interesting. Um there's a famous essay
inside a workplace somewhere and the
title of it is like go where you're rare
or something like that. Oh and this kind
of reminds me of that. It's a scarce
thing that you could solve that problem.
And yeah, you know, it makes sense, man.
I haven't seen that essay. I love that.
Yeah. Yeah. There's a lot of gold in
workplace actually. A lot of people
sleep on on the like the alltime essays
in in workplace. Yeah. They're buried
somewhere in there. There's another one
from one of our like I don't know ICT
10s that we have at the company who
talks about the
20% of the time he just works on stuff
that like he's never going to get
credited for, right? Right. It's like
the kind of org contributions or if you
get very senior, it might be the code
contributions cuz like they don't really
care if I code Yeah. or not anymore,
right? What's the rationale that if
you're always if you spend 100% of your
time working on stuff that you get
credited for, you're probably dropping a
lot of stuff, right? And I see I see it
happen like someone might come and be
like, "Hey, can you like help me with
this thing or something like that?" And
I'll be like, "Well, I I'm know I'm
never going to get credit for this, so I
just say no to But there was actually a
lot of value in helping that person. I'm
just like when performance comes around,
no one's going to be like, "Oh, he
helped this person. Cool." So, I
actually like that kind of mindset and
it was kind of how I was operating
before I read this, too. But like, yeah.
20 or 30% of my time. Yeah. I'll just do
things that I know I'm not going to get
credited for. Yeah. Yeah. PSC is all
about doing things that are measurable.
And there can be a hundred little things
that you help people with that made them
5% better or something and that's not
going to be in your PSC because your PSC
is probably just giant migration item,
giant, you know, this, giant that. Not
all those little things. Not all the
little things. And like those 20 or 30%
you want them to from your point of
view, you think they're valuable, right?
But just no one else is going to think
they're valuable. Like I think helping
that person is valuable. I think doing
things for the org, the wider or is
valable. I think having some coding time
is valuable, right? But yeah, a lot of
people like probably not. Yeah. Yeah. I
think also early in my career, I I
worked so much extra hours just doing
whatever people gave me that I do think
it actually became valuable at a later
time. Like, you know, I was kn credible
and known as someone who's just going to
like unblock you no matter what. Like,
I'll be responding late or whatever just
cuz I was into it. Yeah. So there's a
hidden things outside of PSC that Yeah.
And then that becomes valuable, right?
Yeah. And then that becomes value. Yeah.
Like a lot of people appreciate the fact
that I'm a senior engineer who still
codes. I think we talked about the work
diary thing. I wrote something about how
it's important to have some
documentation of the things you're
landing or the state of investigations
etc. and the value of writing. What's
your process for keeping track of your
work in writing? Oh yeah. So basically I
have a really good note takingaking
system because I'm terrible at
remembering things. So and my
note-taking system is actually in VS
Code. Oh really? Yeah. So I just have
another VS Code instance spun up so I
can have two running or whatever. Is it
just a text? It's just a text. Yeah. And
uh so I'll have it and I don't I don't
actually use multiple monitors. So I
just have like the workspace thing or
whatever on Mac where I can just use a
couple of fingers and it just flicks
across. Oh, like that. Okay. So it's
always very easily accessible and I'll
just dive across and I'll have I'll
create a new readme file in one folder.
I don't have the whole I don't have a
folder archive. It's just one folder and
I'll have like Yeah. like current
project name or something just saved in
there. Yeah. And that way I can like
search for a file name in like two or
three characters and jump between file
names. So I have now on there there's
probably like tens of thousands of files
cuz I have notes for everything on
there. Yeah. But I this is my like index
way of like sort of jumping between lots
of thoughts. Yeah. And writing them
down. And then I have like keyboard
shortcuts for inserting like the current
date and time. Yeah. Right. So I can
like kind of index it on that. Oh wow.
It's like an extension of your brain.
Just like you're just constantly noting
things down at all. Constantly noting it
down and I don't have to spend any time
organizing it, right? Cuz there is no
folder structure. Just one giant thing.
The only thing that it's organized by is
like searching for a file name. Or you
can use word search, right, if you need
to. F. Yeah. Crl+ F. But most of the
time I'm like have a pretty good idea of
what thing I saved it under. Right.
Yeah. So every oneonone there's like a a
name of a person, right? Like Right.
Right. Right. Every project there's one
I have like a couple of root level ones
like
priorities. For work there's priorities.
So then in there I'll have use the time
stamp each day. These are the priority
things. Write some memos for me up the
top like you know don't spend time on X
today, right? or like this year, don't
spend time on this. Like, don't focus on
why. Yeah. Yeah. Which is actually
helpful reminders because I'll jump in
there once a week and be like, "Oh crap,
I'm trying to break that habit." Yeah.
Yeah. I'll get out of this. So, I guess
that's you writing things in and
cataloging when you pull like let's say
you're writing your performance review.
That's one reason people like use. Yes.
So, you just kind of dive through there.
Is there like one that's like
achievements or like So I've only once
in my career for a year kept track of
the projects and stuff that I did. Um
and yeah, this year I'm not keeping
track again. Okay. So yeah, I don't keep
track of what is actually happening on
the like Okay. So you just at the end
you just end I'll try to figure it out.
Which has downsides, right? You know, it
takes like a whole day to figure out
what you did for the year. Yeah. Yeah.
But yeah, I just haven't found value in
tracking everything each day. Yeah.
Yeah. because I already have like the
system of like what I need. Yeah, I mean
dailies probably be too much anyways.
Like I feel I always liked writing
launch posts because at the end of the
year I just scroll through what just
every launch post is like a bullet in my
PC. So that's a good one. I like that
because you got to put those out anyway,
right? So yeah, you got to put those out
anyways. So it's just like I'll just
look at those later. Yeah. Okay. I like
that that note-taking. It's simple. It's
it's simple. And then the other thing
that's part of it is there there are
links between the files. Oh. Uh so I
have a VS code extension which lets me
put links between the files very easily.
Yeah. Yeah. So I can just and it's I
don't know it's like I press one key and
same because I'm using everything based
on the file name, right? I just like
start typing file name. Bang. It's
linked. Yeah. So that's the way that
it's kind of organized. I can like jump
between these thoughts or whatever.
Yeah. And then it actually has a the
same VS code extension has this thing
where you can view it as a graph. So if
you started linking all your files
together, you can then view a graph and
see how you've like organized your mind
and you're like, "Holy
[__] well that's gimmicky." Like I
never use it that like occasionally you
fire it up, you're like, "Wow." It's
like your own internal Wikipedia like
what you got going on like linking
between thoughts and Yeah. Exactly. And
then once you've been doing it for a
while now I've been doing it for like 10
years or something. It's just like 10
years of thoughts in there. And I have
all my personal stuff in there, too,
right? It's kind of weird cuz then you
see the work and the personal overlap at
some point. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. I
wonder if it can you could feed it to an
LLM one day and it can Oh, yeah. useful
or something. You can retrieve that
easier. Yeah. Yeah. It'll like know
everything about me. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
Cuz it's got my diary in there, too.
It's got like all sorts of things. Yeah.
Oh, that is so cool. I see we're like
low on time. So, the last thing that I
want to ask you is let's say you were
going back into the industry. This is
like you just graduated college. Yep.
And you were going to give yourself some
advice. What would you what would you
say?
Oh, man. Well, okay. Go where you're
valued. I've seen lots of people go onto
teams where they're not val not valued.
Like, what do you mean they're not
valued? Like you're you're really good
at working on front end, right? and then
you end up on a backend team and all of
a sudden your performance is crap or
like you're really good at
fixing or like you like working on
framework things and you're on a product
team and you're like constantly tweaking
the frameworks and making them better
and then you get a really bad rating at
the end of the year even though you
landed like 500 diffs or something.
Yeah. Yeah. Like go into the environment
in which like you're valued and maybe
you end up being an environment you're
not valued in for a year but just like
recognize that and get out of it. Right.
Right. So I think so like lean into your
strengths basically. Yeah. You're you're
trying to lean into your strengths but
the your management chain or your team
around you doesn't care about your
strengths, right? Go and find a team
that like likes your strengths and go
there, right? And you're going to be way
happier. It's going to work much better
for you. Yeah, definitely. And it seems
like your career, that's kind of where
it started to you made that jump into a
web team. Yeah. Instagram. You were
excited about it and you just kind of
went up from there. Yeah. Exactly.
General philosophy is just like I don't
know, be nice, be be good. What's the
word? Have have fun. Like I I'm always
being a joker, right? Like even even
when I'm talking to leadership or like
writing out these big posts, right? Like
most of the time they're not super
professional. I'm trying to be like, you
know, have a little bit of fun with it.
Yeah. Be be simple, right? Don't over
complicate your posts orification. I
mean a lot of people they present like a
work you know a work form of themselves
and then uh you know outside of work
they're a different person. Yeah. So
yeah I try to meld those things for me I
try to do the do the same thing cuz
that's like kind of true to me and like
I think makes makes work more
interesting and we're like we're having
to work on it. We spend a lot of time
here. Right. It' be more fun. But I
wonder why there's got to be some
trade-off because it seems like so many
people are Yeah. What's the tradeoff? I
think like depending on the type of
person you are, like sometimes I can end
up saying really dumb stuff, right?
Yeah. And then the way that I've had to
counter this at work, people know that
like, "Oh, Jake's very nice." And if he
says something dumb and you tell him,
he'll like be like, "Oh, yeah, [__]
Sorry, that was dumb." and like
apologize for it and like Yeah. stuff
like this. Obviously, can't go out and
say like really crazy stuff, but
thankfully I don't do that in my
personal life anyway. But yeah, I try to
bring my like I don't know myself to
work. Thanks for listening to this
podcast. I hope that it was helpful.
This podcast is a hobby of mine and so
I'm not selling anything and I don't
have any sponsors, but if you want to
support the podcast, please drop a like.
If you're on YouTube or wherever you're
listening to this, if you're on Spotify
or Apple Podcast, if you could leave a
review, that would be much appreciated.
And I'm always looking for new people to
interview. So, if you have any
suggestions on that, people you think
would be interesting to bring on to the
podcast, please let me know with a
comment and I'll take a look.